Inventory of the George W. Landau papers
Hoover Institution Archives
George W. Landau papers
1942-2006
2007C19
Landau, George W., 1920-
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings and other printed matter, and video tapes, relating to American relations with Paraguay, Chile, Venezuela, and other countries in Latin America.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
George W. Landau was born in Vienna, Austria, in 1920. He became a naturalized citizen of the United States of America in 1943. In 1942, he joined the United States Army as a private and had achieved the rank of Captain by the end of his active duty in 1947. His fluency in German and his Austrian origin made him valuable to the United States Military Intelligence Service in Austria during World War II. In 1947, Landau became an active reserve officer until he retired as a Colonel in 1975.
From 1942 to 1955, George W. Landau was an assistant vice-president at Inta-Mar Shipping Corp, in charge of the Latin-American Division of the international freight forwarder. In 1955, he worked in Colombia as the general manager of a distributor for Chrysler. In 1957, he entered the Foreign Service of the U.S. Department of State and was stationed in Montevideo, Uruguay, as the commercial attaché and chief of the economic section until 1962. From 1962 to 1965 he worked as the supervising political officer in Madrid, Spain. He attended the Canadian National Defense College in Ontario from 1965-1966.
Between 1966 and 1972, Landau worked as the country director in the Office of Spanish and Portuguese Affairs at the State Department in Washington. He became the ambassador to Paraguay in 1972 and remained there until 1977. His career as ambassador to Paraguay was marked by the controversy surrounding the Letelier Case. Orlando Letelier, the former Chilean defense minister in the government of Salvador Allende, was assassinated in Washington, DC in 1976. Landau served as the ambassador to Chile from 1977 until 1982. His career in Chile was defined by his involvement in the resolution of the Beagle Channel Conflict between Chile and Argentina regarding control of islands and waterways strategically located off the southern edge of Tierra del Fuego. He was nominated as the ambassador to Guatemala in 1980, but the nomination was aborted. Landau served as the ambassador to Venezuela from 1982 to 1985.
From 1985 to 1993, he was the President of the Council of the Americas and Americas Society. During his time with the council he served on the boards of several private companies with interests in South America. In 1993, Landau retired as President of the council and moved to Florida with his wife, Mary Landau.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains documents and video related to the life of George W. Landau, starting with his entrance into active duty with the United States Army during 1942 until his retirement as president of the Council of the Americas and Americas Society in 1993. From George W. Landau's early military career the collection contains military awards, certificates, and intelligence correspondence by the U.S. Army from World War II.
The collection is comprised primarily of diplomatic correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, interviews, clippings, other printed matter and videocassettes, relating to American relations with Spain, Portugal, Paraguay, Chile, Guatemala, and Venezuela during George W. Landau's career in the U.S. Foreign Service. There are documents pertaining to the Letelier Case (the assassination of Orlando Letelier, a Chilean political figure and activist, in Washington, D.C. in 1976) and the Beagle Channel Conflict between Chile and Argentina regarding control of islands and waterways strategically located off the southern edge of Tierra del Fuego.
Further personal and professional correspondence, clippings, and other printed matter exist from his career as president of the Council of the Americas and Americas Society.
Arrangement
The material reflects the original order of the papers when received from the donor.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States. Dept. of State.; United States Foreign relations Paraguay.; Paraguay Foreign relations United States.; United States Foreign relations Chile.; Chile Foreign relations United States.; United States Foreign relations Venezuela.; Venezuela Foreign relations United States.; United States Foreign relations Latin America.; Latin America Foreign relations United States.; Videotapes; Diplomats United States.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1942-1980 (Box 1)
  Documentation on Landau's duty in the U.S. Army as well as certificates and medals of merit
  - U.S. Army, active duty (Private to Captain), 1942-1947 (Folder 1: 1-3)
  - U.S. Army, active reserve 1947 (Captain)-1975 (Colonel)/ retired reserve, 1947-1975 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Certificate of transfer to retired reserve, 1975 (Folder 1: 5)
  - U.S. Department of State, meritorious service medal, 1975 (Folder 1: 6)
  - U.S. Department of State, certificate of appreciation, 1975 (Folder 1: 7)
  - U.S. Department of State, certificate of retirement, 1980 (Folder 1: 8)
- Career Files, 1957-2004 (Box 2-5)
  Materials document Landau's positions within the U.S. Department of State, arranged in the original, roughly chronological, order
  - Entry into Foreign Service and Montevideo, Uruguay, Commercial and Chief Economic Section, 1957-1962 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Commerce Committee for the Alliance for Progress Department of Commerce, May-August 1962 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Madrid, Spain, political officer, October 1962-July 1965 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Canadian Defense College, September 1965-July 1966 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Director of Spanish and Portuguese Affairs, Department of State, July 1966-September 1972 (Folder 2: 5-7)
  - "Exotic Dancer Five," Joint Army-Navy Exercise, May 1972 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Nomination as ambassador to Paraguay, August-September 1972 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Ambassador to Paraguay, congratulatory response, 1972 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - Ambassador to Paraguay, 1972-1977 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Nomination as ambassador to Chile, August-November 1977 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Ambassador to Chile, 1977-1982. (Folder 3: 5)
    See also clippings and videos, boxes 5-8
  - The Letelier Case, Chile, 1976-2006. (Folder 3: 6-7)
  - Aborted Nomination as ambassador to Guatemala, 1980 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Nomination as ambassador to Venezuela, 1982 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Ambassador to Venezuela, August 1982-June 1985 (Folder 4: 3-5)
  - Venezuela, departure and press clippings, May-June 1985 (Folder 4: 6)
  - President to the Council of the Americas and Americas Society, July 1985-September 1993 (Folder 4: 7-9)
  - Board Member, Export-Import Bank of the United States, 1990-1991 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Decoration Awards, Chile and Peru, Chile: November 15, 1993, Peru: May 9, 1994, 1993-1994 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Council of the Americas and Americas Society, farewell and appreciation, 1993 (Folder 5: 3-4)
  - Beagle Channel Conflict reunion ceremony speech, 4 December 1985 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Beagle Channel Conflict, La Segunda serial, 2004 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Oral History Interview, Foreign Affairs Oral History Program, 11 March 1991 (Folder 5: 7)
- Clippings, 1978-1982 (Box 5-7)
  Contains clippings documenting the investigation of the Letelier case
  - U.S. International Communication Agency, Santiago, Chile, newspaper clippings, July 1978-February 1979 (Folder 5: 8-14)
  - U.S. International Communication Agency, Santiago, Chile, newspaper clippings, March 1979-June 1980 (Folder 6: 1-6)
  - U.S. International Communication Agency, Santiago, Chile, newspaper clippings, July 1980-January 1982 (Folder 7: 1-9)
- Video tapes, 1984-1991 (Box 8)
  Includes video tape of Landau on CNN and other shows relating to the Letelier case, Chile and Chilean elections, and Venezuela
  - Chile, BBC, Letelier Case: Insider Story/Assassin (Letelier, Townley), videocassette, 55 minutes, undated (Folder 8: 1)
  - Chile, CNN, videocassette, April 25,1986 (Folder 8: 2)
  - CNN, TV, The International Hour: Professor George Landau on Chile, videocassette, 10 July 1986 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Chile-Election, videocassette, 15 December, circa 1977 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Latin American Business Review, Chile, Program #7, videocassette, 13 December 1991 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Estadia Del Exmo. Embajador George Landau en Caracas, Venezuela, 2 videocassettes, November 1984 - May 1985 (Folder 8: 6-7)